this is the last video in a six-part
series on yoga if you missed any check
out the links in the description below
you'll also find a link to the webinar
that I did on the subject which includes
a q a portion
[Music]
even though for certain health
conditions we have not reached a point
where we can say there's good scientific
evidence that yoga is beneficial many
patients do seem to benefit and isn't
that what matters I mean even in the
studies to show the benefit is mainly a
placebo effect does this really matter I
mean after all this editorial asserted
yoga therapy has never been shown to
have adverse effects but that's simply
not true about 2 000 yoga related
injuries have been seen in hospital
emergency rooms every year from 2001 to
2014.
looks like only one fatalities have been
reported in the medical literature but
if you look at the case report a 16 year
old girl collapsing with a ruptured lung
following voluntary mouth-to-mouth yoga
breathing exercises with a teenage boy
in the hall that can hardly be
characterized as a typical yoga practice
there are tragic rare cases tied to
actual yoga like this quad rupture in a
young woman or God ephemeral fracture
the femur is the bone in your thigh
longest strongest heaviest bone in the
body typically you only see femur
fractures with trauma such as car
crashes but here was just a guy
practicing this yoga posture when he
heard a large cracking sound and felt
immense pain because yikes this is what
happened
now two weeks earlier he had felt pain
in his thigh that he just thought was
muscle strain but bone biopsy showed
evidence of previous micro fractures so
it sounds like he had been overdoing it
weakening it before the final crack so I
guess the bottom line is that people
should listen to their bodies and not
push themselves too far
now my last video I talked about the
risk of spinal compression fractures
particularly those with weakened bones
osteopenia or osteoporosis poses causing
hyperflexion hyperextension of the
sponge should probably be avoided these
were the poses tied to injury in a few
dozen cases of musculoskeletal injuries
described at the Mayo Clinic but case
reports and series of case reports are
really just kind of glorified anecdotes
I mean they don't give you an overall
sense of the safety of yoga if you look
at randomized controlled yoga trials
there's actually no significant
difference in injury rates between the
yoga groups and the control groups that
use some other sort of exercise
intervention now this may not
necessarily translate out into Real
World Experience given the short
duration of yoga in these clinical
trials as little as a single day and the
fact that they may be more closely
supervised with more highly trained
teachers that's why large-scale surveys
like this can be helpful looking at
thousands of people taking yoga classes
looks like about 30 percent of yoga
class attendees had experienced some
type of adverse event most commonly just
something mild like muscle aches but
some individuals did experience more
severe events which caused them to stop
going many causes were associated with
overexertion and overdoing and starting
out in poor physical condition
this systematic review included nine
observational studies with nine thousand
plus yoga practitioners and nine
thousand plus non-yoga practitioners
from the U.S Europe Asia and Australia a
considerable proportion of yoga
practitioners experienced injuries or
other Adverse Events however most were
mild and transient and risks were
comparable to those of non-yoga
practitioners the risk of yoga
Associated injuries was estimated as
1.45 per thousand hours of yoga practice
much lower than in higher Impact Sports
activities such as soccer compared to
1.5 for yoga Runners have like 2.5
injuries per thousand hours Soccer
3.75 for tennis an hour of yoga is more
than five times safer than skiing
here's where yoga falls on the Spectrum
yoga appears much safer for example than
aerobic funk
on the other hand yoga practitioners may
suffer an increased risk of meniscus
injury the main stabilizing and
cushioning cartilage in the knee yoga
was found associated with significantly
higher risk of meniscus injury compared
with activities such as badmin jogging
and climbing Hills some fundamental yoga
postures like the Lotus position can be
hard on the knees yes yoga poses can
undoubtedly improve the flexibility of
the knee but in moderate joint movement
can pose a serious threat
the bottom line is like any other type
of physical activity yoga carries a risk
of injury exercise is indeed medicine
but like any medicine it must be
prescribed appropriately many patients
rely on their yoga practice for stress
reduction so it's important to be
mindful that being injured is the last
thing you need
the higher risk yoga poses appear to
include headstands shoulder stands Lotus
and half Lotus forward bends backward
bends and handstands and so beginners
should be aware with particular
attention paid to the spine as this is
where the highest numbers of injuries
occur
Hot Yoga deserves special mention the
extreme heat and intensity of Bikram
Yoga may make it inappropriate for older
adults and people with medical
conditions but there are case reports
like this one of sudden Cardiac Arrest
even in a healthy 35 year old
pregnancy is an especially vulnerable
time for heat exposure with the
increased risk of spinal defects and
possibly other birth defects among
fetuses exposed to excessive heat
pregnant women should avoid practicing
Hot Yoga during pregnancy maternal
hyperthermia whether from a sauna or
electric blankets had a nearly two-fold
increased risk of spinal and brain
malformations
for example pregnant women who use hot
tubs increase the risk of bearing babies
with their intestines outside their
bodies or being born without a brain
as any other physical or mental practice
yoga should be practiced carefully under
the guidance of a qualified instructor
beginners should avoid extreme practices
such as headstand Lotus position
forceful breathing individuals with
medical preconditions should work with
their physician and yoga teacher to
appropriately adapt postures for example
patients with glaucoma should avoid
upside down positions and patients with
compromised bones should avoid forceful
Yoga practices and practices like
voluntary vomiting should perhaps be
avoided completely
what it's evidently common practice in
traditional yoga
[Music]